Max Peterson Oral History Project 198
People's Archive, MLK Library
Max Peterson Oral History Project
1931-2021, undated
2020-10-2021-03
People's Archive, MLK Library
Peterson, Max
Hunt, Isaac Cosby, III, 1971-
Crutchfield, Edith Amanda, 1936-
198
26.2 Gigabytes DIG_00029
37 Files DIG_00029
Arrangement
Interviews are group into two series: Series 1: Cosby Hunt Series 2: Edith Crutchield
Biographical / Historical
Max Peterson is an educator at The Center for Inspired Teaching and has been co-teacher of Real World History since 2017. Mr. Peterson completed these interviews in connection to his thesis work for Columbia University's Oral History Master of Arts program.
Custodial History
Max Peterson donated the collection to DC Public Library in 2020.
Related Materials
Collection 194: Center for Inspired Teaching 'Real World History' Oral History Project
Content Description
The Max Peterson Oral History Project is a companion project to the Center for Inspired Teaching 'Real World History' Oral History Project. This project includes interviews with Cosby Hunt, a native Washingtonian and creator of the Real World History Class, and Ms. Edith Crutchfield, a long-time D.C. resident who moved to Washington from Culpeper, Virginia, in 1953. Ms. Crutchfield first became involved with Real World History when she collaborated on an oral history project with a student in the fall of 2018. Ms. Edith's interview from Real World History can be found in the Center for Inspired Teaching 'Real World History' Oral History Project. The interviews in this collection, of both Mr. Hunt and Ms. Crutchfield, take a life history approach in which the interviewees discuss some of their life experiences beginning with their early life. Over the course of several interviews, Mr. Hunt discusses his upbringing in Washington, his career as a high school history teacher, and the development of the Real World History Class; Ms. Edith discusses her upbringing in Culpeper, her move to Washington in 1953, and her life and career in the District.
Migration, Internal; Families; African Americans; Oral History; Black people
- Series 1: Cosby Hunt, 1931 -2020, undated
  Biographical / Historical
  Isaac Cosby Hunt III (b. 12/11/1971) is a high school history teacher in Washington, D.C., and a native Washingtonian. Cosby is the only child of Isaac Cosby Hunt Jr. and Elizabeth Dollie Ravenell Hunt. Cosby grew up in the Hawthorne neighborhood of D.C. and attended Lafayette Elementary School and St. Albans School before graduating from University of Pennsylvania in Philadelphia. Upon completing his undergraduate degree, Cosby began his teaching career by joining Teach for America in 1993. After teaching social studies in Hancock County, Georgia, for two years, Cosby enrolled in a graduate program at the University of Georgia and earned his master's in education. Upon graduating from UGA, Cosby returned to Washington, D.C., to become a public school teacher and taught at Bell Multicultural High School (now CHEC - Columbia Heights Education Campus). Cosby taught at Bell for thirteen years before joining Center for Inspired Teaching in the summer of 2010. After three years of working with D.C. high school teachers through Center for Inspired Teaching, Cosby developed and piloted the Real World History program, an after-school, honors history course available to high school students in D.C. Public Schools, in the fall of 2014. In SY 2019-2020, Cosby returned to full-time teaching and began working at Thurgood Marshall Academy Public Charter School in Anacostia. Cosby earned his National Board Certification in 2006 and has received many awards throughout his teaching career, including District of Columbia History Teacher of the Year in 2008 and National History Day Teacher of the Year in 2019.
  - Sub-Series 1: Interviews, 2020-10
    - Session 1, 2020-10-13; Hunt, Isaac Cosby, III, 1971-; Peterson, Max
      Scope and Contents
      This is the first session of a life history interview with Cosby Hunt, a career educator, native Washingtonian, and creator of Real World History at the Center for Inspired Teaching. In this interview Cosby Hunt reflects on this his family background, his parent's lives, and his early life in Washington, D.C., in the 1970s and 1980s.
    - Session 2, 2020-10-20; Hunt, Isaac Cosby, III, 1971-; Peterson, Max
      This is the second session of a life history interview with Cosby Hunt, a career educator, native Washingtonian, and creator of Real World History at the Center for Inspired Teaching. In this interview Cosby Hunt discusses some early memories but mainly focuses on his adolescent years and high school experience. He talks about a variety of subjects including: visits to Danville, Virginia, to visit his father's family, his mother's parents in Boston, Massachusetts, his interest in painting as a young man, developing a Black identity in high school, his favorite teachers from St. Albans, his first experiences with loss as a high schooler, and the death of his mother when he was 23 years old.
    - Session 3, 2020-10-27; Hunt, Isaac Cosby, III, 1971-; Peterson, Max
      This is the third session of a life history interview with Cosby Hunt, a career educator, native Washingtonian, and creator of Real World History at the Center for Inspired Teaching. In this interview Cosby Hunt discusses his college experience at the University of Pennsylvania, teaching in Hancock County, Georgia, through Teach for America, and his experience attending graduate school at the University of Georgia.
    - Session 4, 2021-01-21; Hunt, Isaac Cosby, III, 1971-; Peterson, Max
      This is the fourth session of a life history interview with Cosby Hunt, a career educator, native Washingtonian, and creator of Real World History. In this interview Cosby Hunt discusses returning to Washington, D.C., after finishing graduate school at the University of Georgia, his teaching career at Bell Multicultural High School (1997-2010), and his family life, including how he met his wife and how they named their two sons.
      African Americans; Teachers; High Schools; Families; Community organization; Education; Gentrification; Statehood (American politics); Black people
    - Session 5, 2021-02-25; Hunt, Isaac Cosby, III, 1971-; Peterson, Max
      This is the fifth session of an oral history interview with Cosby Hunt, a career educator, native Washingtonian, and creator of Real World History. In this interview Cosby Hunt discusses his experience working at Center for Inspired Teaching and the creation of the Real World History Program (RWH) in 2014. He also talks about the structure of the program in its first year, school year 2014-2015.
      African Americans; Museums; Art; Teachers; Education; High school students; Black people
    - Session 6, 2021-03-17; Hunt, Isaac Cosby, III, 1971-; Peterson, Max
      This is the sixth and final session of an oral history interview with Cosby Hunt, a career educator, native Washingtonian, and creator of Real World History. In this interview Mr. Hunt discusses the Real World History program and the Real World History Collection at the DC Public Library. He also reflects on what he is most proud of about the class and how the course, in some ways, is connected to his family history.
      African Americans; Art; Teachers; High school students; Migration, Internal; Museums; COVID-19 Pandemic, 2020-; Education; Black people
  - Sub-Series 2: Indexes, 2020-10
    - Session 1 index, 2020-10-13; Hunt, Isaac Cosby, III, 1971-; Peterson, Max
    - Session 2 index, 2020-10-20; Hunt, Isaac Cosby, III, 1971-; Peterson, Max
    - Session 3 index, 2020-10-27; Hunt, Isaac Cosby, III, 1971-; Peterson, Max
    - Session 4 index, 2021-01-21; Hunt, Isaac Cosby, III, 1971-; Peterson, Max
    - Session 5 index, 2021-02-25; Hunt, Isaac Cosby, III, 1971-; Peterson, Max
    - Session 6 index, 2021-03-17; Hunt, Isaac Cosby, III, 1971-; Peterson, Max
  - Sub-Series 3: Transcripts, 2020-10
    - Session 1 transcript, 2020-10-13; Hunt, Isaac Cosby, III, 1971-; Peterson, Max
    - Session 2 transcript, 2020-10-20; Hunt, Isaac Cosby, III, 1971-; Peterson, Max
    - Session 3 transcript, 2020-10-27; Hunt, Isaac Cosby, III, 1971-; Peterson, Max
    - Session 4 transcript, 2021-01-21; Hunt, Isaac Cosby, III, 1971-; Peterson, Max
    - Session 5 transcript, 2021-02-25; Hunt, Isaac Cosby, III, 1971-; Peterson, Max
    - Session 6 transcript, 2021-03-17; Hunt, Isaac Cosby, III, 1971-; Peterson, Max
  - Sub-Section 4: Images, 1931-2019, Undated
    - Evelyn D. Allen's North Carolina Negro Teachers' Association Official Membership Card, 1931-04-03
      A digital image of Evelyn D. Allen's North Carolina Negro Teachers' Association Official Membership Card. Evelyn Allen or 'Eve' was the Cosby Hunt's paternal grandmother. This item is discussed at [00:40:31] of Cosby Hunt Session 1.
      Allen, Evelyn D.
    - National Bankers Association, 1931-04-03
      A digital image of a print photograph of the National Bankers Association posed in front of the Founders Library at Howard University. The photograph includes Cosby Hunt's paternal grandfather Isaac Cosby Hunt, Sr. This item is discussed in Cosby Hunt Session 2.
    - Isaac Cosby Hunt with his mother and paternal grandparents, 1971, ca.
      A digital image of a print photograph of Cosby Hunt as an infant with his mother and paternal grandparents. This item is discussed at [00:40:00.00] Cosby Hunt Session 2.
      Hunt, Isaac Cosby, III, 1971-
    - Eve Hunt's funeral, 1992-04
      A digital image of a polaroid photograph of the funeral of Eve Hunt, paternal grandmother of Cosby Hunt (second from the right). From left to right the men in the imager are Lut Williams, Bravell 'Bucky' Nesbitt, Jerry Williams Jr., Robert Williams, Cosby Hunt, and Cosby's father, Isaac Cosby Hunt Jr. On the backside of the image is the note: 'Eve's Funeral (April '92).' This photograph is discussed at [01:15:40.05].
      Funeral service; Families
    - Looking west down Irving Street, 1998; Hunt, Isaac Cosby, III, 1971-
      A digital image of a photograph that Cosby Hunt took around the time that he began teaching at Bell Multicultural High School. A note on the back of the photograph reads: 'Looking west down Irving Street, 1998.' The title of this image was taken from the caption on the back of the original photograph.
      Streets; Buildings
    - Cosby Hunt with students at Bell Multicultural High School, 1998
      A digital image of a photograph of Cosby Hunt with some of his students at Bell Multicultural High School in 1998.
      High school students; Teachers; Hunt, Isaac Cosby, III, 1971-
    - Cosby Hunt teaching at Bell Multicultural High School, 2000
      A digital image of a photograph of Cosby Hunt teaching at Bell Multicultural High School in the early 2000s.
      Teachers; High Schools; Hunt, Isaac Cosby, III, 1971-
    - Real World History Class at the Phillips Collection, 2014-12-01
      A digital image of a photograph of Real World History students and their narrators perusing Jacob Lawrence's Migration Series at the Phillips Collection. After viewing the panels, each pair recorded an oral history interview about the narrator's experience of moving to Washington, D.C., from the South. Mr. Hunt discusses the group trip at [01:07:51.08].
      Museums; High school students
    - Real World History Class at the Phillips Collection, 2014-12-01
    - Real World History Class at the Museum of Modern Art, 2015-06-01
      A digital image of a photograph of Real World History students and their narrators at the Museum of Modern Art in New York City on a group trip to visit the exhibition 'One Way Ticket: Jacob Lawrence's Migration Series'. Mr. Hunt discusses the group trip at [00:33:03.04].
      High school students; Museums; Hunt, Isaac Cosby, III, 1971-
    - Real World History Class at Thurgood Marshall Academy Public Charter School, 2019
      A digital image of a group photo of the 2019-2020 cohort of Real World History sitting in front of Thurgood Marshall Academy Public Charter School, where the class was taught. Cosby Hunt discusses teaching Real World History and teaching full-time at TMA during the 2019-2020 school year at [01:04:37.08].
      Teachers; High school students; Hunt, Isaac Cosby, III, 1971-
    - Portrait of Richard Allen, Undated
      A digital image of what may be a tintype photograph of Richard Allen, great-grandfather to Cosby Hunt on his father's side. This item is discussed at [00:09:44.25] Cosby Hunt Session 2.
      Allen, Richard
    - Lafayette Elementary School Fifth Grade Class, Undated
      A digital image of a print photograph of Cosby Hunt's fifth grade class photo from Lafayette Elementary School in Washington, D.C. Cosby Hunt is on the far left in the second row. This item is discussed at [00:44:23] Cosby Hunt Session 1.
    - "The Shack", Undated
      A digital image of a print photograph of the house where Cosby Hunt lived while attending graduate school at the University of Georgia. Cosby recalls how he and his friends referred to the house as "the shack." This item is discussed at [01:36:00.10] Cosby Hunt Session 3.
    - The Hunt Family at Cosby Hunt's college graduation, Undated
      A digital image of a photograph of Cosby Hunt with his parents at his college graduation from the University of Georgia. From left to right are Elizabeth R. Hunt ('Betty'), Cosby Hunt, and Isaac C. Hunt Jr. ('Ike'). Cosby discusses the connection between his family history and Real World History at [01:34:52.00].
      Families; Hunt, Isaac Cosby, III, 1971-
    - Cosby Hunt, Sandy Zipp, and Eric Wilson, Undated
      A digital image of framed print photograph of Cosby Hunt (right) and two close friends, Eric Wilson (left) and Sandy Zipp (center). This item is discussed at [01:03:10] Cosby Hunt Session 1.
    - Attendees at a Project PRIDE event, Undated; Hunt, Isaac Cosby, III, 1971-
      A digital image of a photograph from one of the community gatherings that Cosby Hunt organized while teaching Project PRIDE (Parents Roots Inspire a Dedication to Education) at Bell Multicultural High School. Mr. Hunt discusses the community gatherings at [00:57:28.25].
      Families; High Schools
    - Real World History Class at Cardozo High School, Undated
      A digital image of a photograph of Cosby Hunt teaching a Real World History class outside of Cardozo High School. After five years at Cardozo (School year 2014-2015 through 2018-2019), the Real World History program moved to Thurgood Marshall Academy in the fall of 2019.
      High Schools; Teachers; Hunt, Isaac Cosby, III, 1971-
  - Sub-Series 5: Miscellaneous, 2017
    - English period III profile, 2017-12
      A profile completed by a student in the Real World History Class of a narrator with annotations from Cosby Hunt in red.
      Education
- Series 2: Edith Crutchfield, 2020-10-2020-12
  Ms. Edith Amanda Crutchfield, born August 28, 1936, is a retired librarian and native of Culpeper, Virginia. Ms. Edith is the daughter of John Duff Grasty and Sarah George Ross Grasty and is one of 10 sisters. She migrated to Washington, D.C. at the age of 17 after finishing high school in Culpeper and has remained in D.C. for the rest of her life. All 10 of Ms. Edith's sisters migrated north after high school and none of them returned to live in Virginia. Ms. Edith initially lived with sisters and other family upon arriving in Washington and attended Howard University for a semester before transferring to Miner Teachers College just as Miner's and Wilson Teachers College were being integrated and combined into DC Teachers College. Ms. Edith had a 30-year career as a librarian in government libraries (FDA and DOJ) and spent the last fifteen years of her career in private libraries of law firms. Ms. Edith married and had one daughter, Debra, who passed away in 2015.
  - Sub-Series 1: Interviews, 2020-10-2020-12
    - Session 1, 2020-10-24; Crutchfield, Edith Amanda, 1936-; Peterson, Max
      This is the first session of a life history interview with Edith Crutchfield. In this interview Ms. Crutchfield primarily discusses her early life in Culpeper, Virginia, before moving to Washington, D.C., at age 17 in 1953. In discussing her upbringing, Ms. Edith talks extensively about her family life with her parents and nine sisters. She talks about her parents work and explains that she and all her sisters began domestic work at age 11. Ms. Edith also discusses her educational experiences at segregated schools in Culpeper and recounts some of her early experiences in Washington, such as attending Miner Teachers College when the school merged with Wilson Teachers College to become the integrated DC Teachers College.
    - Session 2, 2020-10-31; Crutchfield, Edith Amanda, 1936-; Peterson, Max
      This is the second session of a life history interview with Edith Crutchfield. In this interview Ms. Crutchfield reflects on her upbringing in Culpeper, Virginia, the move to Washington, D.C., in 1953 at age 17, and her life in Washington. She speaks about her experiences with segregation and discrimination in D.C. and discusses how she and her sisters helped each other transition into life in Washington. Ms. Crutchfield recalls being able to vote for the first time when the District was allowed to vote in the 1964 presidential election and relates the civil rights struggles of the 1960s to the 2020 election as well as contemporary social justice struggles. Ms. Crutchfield also discusses her time at Howard University as well as her experience at Miner Teachers College in 1955 when the school merged with Wilson Teachers College to create DC Teachers College. She also reflects on her experiences as a librarian at the FDA and DEA libraries and discusses racism and discrimination she witnessed while working for the government.
    - Session 3, 2020-12-06; Crutchfield, Edith Amanda, 1936-; Peterson, Max
      This is the third session of a life history interview with Ms. Edith Crutchfield. This interview was recorded at three different locations in the Park View and Petworth neighborhoods of Washington, D.C. The first two locations, 3316 Warder Street NW and 4125 New Hampshire Ave NW, are residences where Ms. Crutchfield lived in the years after she first arrived in Washington in August 1953. The final location is Ms. Crutchfield's current home on Rock Creek Church Road NW. In this interview Ms. Edith discusses her experiences in Washington from the 1950s when she first arrived, to 1978 when she moved to Silver Spring,\Maryland. She also recounts how and why she returned to Washington in 2011 and reflects on her life in the D.C. Region. She also discusses her family life in Washington and the lives of her daughter, Debra, and her husband, Richard, who passed away in 2015 and 2018 respectively.
  - Sub-Series 2: Indexes, 2020-10-2020-12
    - Session 1 index, 2020-10-24; Crutchfield, Edith Amanda, 1936-; Peterson, Max
    - Session 2 index, 2020-10-31; Crutchfield, Edith Amanda, 1936-; Peterson, Max
    - Session 3 index, 2020-12-06; Crutchfield, Edith Amanda, 1936-; Peterson, Max
  - Sub-Series 3: Transcripts, 2020-10-2020-12
    - Session 1 transcript, 2020-10-24; Crutchfield, Edith Amanda, 1936-; Peterson, Max
    - Session 2 transcript, 2020-10-31; Crutchfield, Edith Amanda, 1936-; Peterson, Max
    - Session 3 transcript, 2020-12-06; Crutchfield, Edith Amanda, 1936-; Peterson, Max